<?xml version="1.0" encoding="us-ascii"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY rfc3920 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3920.xml">
  <!ENTITY rfc3921 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3921.xml">
  <!ENTITY xep0124 PUBLIC "" "http://xmpp.org/extensions/refs/reference.XSF.XEP-0124.xml">
  <!ENTITY xep0199 PUBLIC "" "http://xmpp.org/extensions/refs/reference.XSF.XEP-0199.xml">
  <!ENTITY xep0206 PUBLIC "" "http://xmpp.org/extensions/refs/reference.XSF.XEP-0206.xml">
  <!ENTITY websocket PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-hybi-thewebsocketprotocol-03.xml">
  <!ENTITY xml PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml4/reference.W3C.REC-xml-20081126.xml">
]>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc rfcprocack="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc linkmailto="yes"?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>

<rfc docName="draft-moffitt-xmpp-over-websocket-00"
     category="std" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="XMPP over WebSocket">
      An XMPP Sub-protocol for WebSocket
    </title>
    
    <author initials="J." surname="Moffitt" fullname="Jack Moffitt"
            role="editor">
      <organization></organization>
      <address>
        <email>jack@metajack.im</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="E." surname="Cestari" fullname="Eric Cestari">
      <organization>ProcessOne</organization>
      <address>
        <email>ecestari@process-one.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="8" month="December" year="2010"/>

    <area>Applications</area>
    <workgroup>HyBi Working Group</workgroup>

    <keyword>I-D</keyword>
    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
    <keyword>WebSocket</keyword>
    <keyword>XMPP</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>
        This document defines a binding for the XMPP protocol over a
        WebSocket transport layer. A WebSocket binding for XMPP
        provides higher performance than the current HTTP binding for
        XMPP.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>
        Applications using XMPP (see <xref target="RFC3920"/> and
        <xref target="RFC3921"/>) on the Web currently make use of
        BOSH (see <xref target="XEP-0124"/> and <xref
        target="XEP-0206"/>), an XMPP binding to HTTP. BOSH is based
        on the HTTP long polling technique, and it suffers from high
        transport overhead compared to XMPP's native binding to TCP.
      </t>
      <t>
        It would be much better in most circumstances to avoid
        tunneling XMPP over HTTP long polled connections and instead
        use the XMPP protocol directly. However, the APIs and sandbox
        that browsers have provided do not allow this. The WebSocket
        protocol <xref target="I-D.ietf-hybi-thewebsocketprotocol"/>
        now exists to solve these kinds of problems. The WebSocket
        protocol is a bi-directional protocol that provides a simple
        message-based framing layer over raw sockets and allows for more
        robust and efficient communication in web applications.
      </t>
      <t>
        This document defines a binding of the XMPP protocol over the
        WebSocket protocol transport. It makes using XMPP within web
        applications simpler and more efficient.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>
        The basic unit of framing in the WebSocket protocol is called
        a message. In XMPP, the basic unit is the stanza, which is a
        subset of the first-level children of each document in an XMPP
        stream (see Section 9 of <xref target="RFC3920"/>). XMPP also
        has a concept of messages, which are stanzas whose top-level
        element name is message. In this document, the word "message"
        will mean a WebSocket message, not an XMPP message stanza (see
        <xref target="messages"/>).
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="XMPP Sub-Protocol">
      <section title="Handshake">
        <t>
          The xmpp sub-protocol is used to transport XMPP over a
          WebSocket connection. The client and server agree to this
          protocol during the WebSocket handshake (see Section 1.3 of
          <xref target="I-D.ietf-hybi-thewebsocketprotocol"/>).
        </t>
        <t>
          During the WebSocket handshake, the client MUST include the
          |Sec-WebSocket-Protocol| header in its handshake, and the
          value |xmpp| must be included in the list of protocols. The
          reply from the server MUST also contain |xmpp| in its own
          |Sec-WebSocket-Protocol| header in order for an XMPP
          sub-protocol connection to be established.
        </t>
        <t>
          Once the handshake is complete, WebSocket messages sent or
          received will conform to the protocol defined in the rest of
          this document.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Messages" anchor="messages">
        <t>
          Data frame messages in the XMPP sub-protocol MUST be of the
          text type and contain UTF-8 encoded data. The close control
          frame's contents are specified in <xref
          target="closing"/>. Control frames other than close are not
          restricted.
        </t>
        <t>
          Unless noted in text, the word "message" will mean a
          WebSocket message containing a text data frame.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="XMPP Stream Setup" anchor="setup">
        <t>
          The first message sent after the handshake is complete MUST
          be an XMPP opening stream tag as defined in XMPP <xref
          target="RFC3920"/> or an XML text declaration (see Section
          4.3.1 of <xref target="W3C.REC-xml-20081126"/>) followed by
          an XMPP opening stream tag. The stream tag MUST NOT be
          closed (i.e. the closing &lt;/stream:stream> tag should not
          appear in the message) as it is the start of the client's
          outgoing XML. The '&lt;' character of the tag or text
          declaration MUST be the first character of the text payload.
        </t>
        <t>
          The server MUST respond with a message containing an error
          (see <xref target="errors"/>), its own opening stream tag,
          or an XML text declaration followed by an opening stream
          tag.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Stream Errors" anchor="errors">
        <t>
          Stream level errors in XMPP are terminal. Should such an
          error occur, the server MUST send the stream error as a
          complete element in a message to the client. This message
          MAY include the closing stream tag if a stream is opened.
        </t>
        <t>
          If the error occurs during the opening of a stream, the
          stream error message MUST start with an opening stream tag
          (see Section 4.7.1 of <xref target="RFC3920"/>) and end with
          a closing stream tag.
        </t>
        <t>
          After the stream error and closing stream tag have been
          sent, the server MUST close the connection as in <xref
          target="closing"/>.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Closing the Connection" anchor="closing">
        <t>
          Either the server or the client may close the connection at
          any time. Before closing the connection, the closing party
          MUST close the XMPP stream if it has been established.  To
          initiate the close, the closing party MUST send a normal
          WebSocket close message with an empty body. The connection
          is considered closed when a matching close message is
          received (see Section 1.4 of <xref
          target="I-D.ietf-hybi-thewebsocketprotocol"/>).
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Stanzas">
        <t>
          Each XMPP stanza MUST be sent in its own message. A stanza
          MUST NOT be split over multiple messages. All first level
          children of the &lt;stream:stream> element MUST be treated
          the same as stanzas (e.g. &lt;stream:features> and
          &lt;stream:error>).
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Stream Restarts">
        <t>
          After successful SASL authentication, an XMPP stream must be
          restarted. In these cases, as soon as the message is sent
          (or received) containing the success indication, both the
          server and client streams are implicitly closed, and new
          streams must be opened. The client MUST open a new stream as
          in <xref target="setup"/> and MUST NOT send a closing stream
          tag.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Pings and Keepalives">
        <t>
          XMPP servers send whitespace pings as keepalives between
          stanzas, and XMPP clients can do the same thing. These extra
          whitespace characters are not significant in the protocol.
          Servers and clients SHOULD use WebSocket ping messages
          instead for this purpose.
        </t>
        <t>
          The XMPP Ping extension <xref target="XEP-0199"/> allows
          entities to send and respond to ping requests. A client
          sending a WebSocket ping is equivalent to pinging the
          WebSocket server, which may also be the XMPP server. When
          the XMPP server is not also the WebSocket server, a
          WebSocket ping may be useful to check the health of the
          intermediary server.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="TLS" anchor="tls">
        <t>
          TLS cannot be used in The XMPP sub-protocol because the
          sub-protocol does not allow for raw binary data to be
          sent. A server MUST NOT advertise TLS as a stream feature
          (see Section 4.6 of <xref target="RFC3920"/>). A client MUST
          ignore the TLS feature if it is advertised over WebSocket.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Examples">
      <t>
        Examples will be added as soon as the WebSocket protocol
        specification is more stable.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>
        If a registry is created for WebSocket sub-protocols, the xmpp
        sub-protocol will be registered.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>
        Since application level TLS cannot be used (see <xref
        target="tls"/>), applications which need to protect the privacy
        of the XMPP traffic need to do so a the WebSocket level or
        some other higher level.
      </t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Informative References">
      &rfc3920;
      &rfc3921;
      &xep0124;
      &xep0199;
      &xep0206;
      &websocket;
      &xml;
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>