<?xml version="1.0" encoding="us-ascii"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc rfcprocack="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc linkmailto="yes"?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>

<rfc docName="draft-moffitt-xmpp-over-websocket-02"
     category="std" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="XMPP over WebSocket">
      An XMPP Sub-protocol for WebSocket
    </title>

    <author initials="L." surname="Stout" fullname="Lance Stout"
            role="editor">
      <organization>&amp;yet</organization>
      <address>
        <email>lance@andyet.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>
   
    <author initials="J." surname="Moffitt" fullname="Jack Moffitt">
      <organization></organization>
      <address>
        <email>jack@metajack.im</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="E." surname="Cestari" fullname="Eric Cestari">
      <organization>ProcessOne</organization>
      <address>
        <email>ecestari@process-one.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="25" month="February" year="2013"/>

    <area>Applications</area>
    <workgroup>HyBi Working Group</workgroup>

    <keyword>I-D</keyword>
    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
    <keyword>WebSocket</keyword>
    <keyword>XMPP</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>
        This document defines a binding for the XMPP protocol over a
        WebSocket transport layer. A WebSocket binding for XMPP
        provides higher performance than the current HTTP binding for
        XMPP.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>
        Applications using XMPP (see <xref target="RFC6120"/>
        and <xref target="RFC6121"/>) on the Web currently make
        use of BOSH (see <xref target="XEP-0124"/> and 
        <xref target="XEP-0206"/>), an XMPP binding to HTTP. BOSH is 
        based on the HTTP long polling technique, and it suffers from
        high transport overhead compared to XMPP's native binding
        to TCP. In addition, there are a number of other known
        issues with long polling <xref target="RFC6202"/>, which have
        an impact on BOSH-based systems.
      </t>
      <t>
        It would be much better in most circumstances to avoid
        tunneling XMPP over HTTP long polled connections and instead
        use the XMPP protocol directly. However, the APIs and sandbox
        that browsers have provided do not allow this. The WebSocket
        protocol <xref target="RFC6455"/> now exists to solve these
        kinds of problems. The WebSocket protocol is a bi-directional
        protocol that provides a simple message-based framing layer
        over raw sockets and allows for more robust and efficient
        communication in web applications.
      </t>
      <t>
        The WebSocket protocol enables two-way communication
        between a client and a server, effectively emulating TCP
        at the application layer and therefore overcoming many of
        the problems with existing long-polling techniques for
        bidirectional HTTP. This document defines a WebSocket
        sub-protocol for the Extensible Messaging and Presence
        Protocol (XMPP).
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>
        The basic unit of framing in the WebSocket protocol is called
        a message. In XMPP, the basic unit is the stanza, which is a
        subset of the first-level children of each document in an XMPP
        stream (see Section 9 of <xref target="RFC6120"/>). XMPP also
        has a concept of messages, which are stanzas whose top-level
        element name is message. In this document, the word "message"
        will mean a WebSocket message, not an XMPP message stanza (see
        <xref target="messages"/>).
      </t>
      <t>
        The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
        NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
        "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described
        in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="XMPP Sub-Protocol">
      <section title="Handshake">
        <t>
          The XMPP sub-protocol is used to transport XMPP over a
          WebSocket connection. The client and server agree to this
          protocol during the WebSocket handshake (see Section 1.3 of
          <xref target="RFC6455"/>).
        </t>
        <t>
          During the WebSocket handshake, the client MUST include the
          |Sec-WebSocket-Protocol| header in its handshake, and the
          value |xmpp| MUST be included in the list of protocols. The
          reply from the server MUST also contain |xmpp| in its own
          |Sec-WebSocket-Protocol| header in order for an XMPP
          sub-protocol connection to be established.
        </t>
        <t>
          Once the handshake is complete, WebSocket messages sent or
          received will conform to the protocol defined in the rest of
          this document.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Messages" anchor="messages">
        <t>
          Data frame messages in the XMPP sub-protocol MUST be of the
          text type and contain UTF-8 encoded data. The close control
          frame's contents are specified in <xref
          target="closing"/>. Control frames other than close are not
          restricted.
        </t>
        <t>
          Unless noted in text, the word "message" will mean a
          WebSocket message containing a text data frame.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="XMPP Stream Setup" anchor="setup">
        <t>
          The first message sent after the handshake is complete MUST
          be an XMPP opening stream tag as defined in XMPP <xref
          target="RFC6120"/> or an XML text declaration (see Section
          4.3.1 of <xref target="W3C.REC-xml-20081126"/>) followed by
          an XMPP opening stream tag. The stream tag MUST NOT be
          closed (i.e. the closing &lt;/stream:stream> tag should not
          appear in the message) as it is the start of the client's
          outgoing XML. The '&lt;' character of the tag or text
          declaration MUST be the first character of the text payload.
        </t>
        <t>
          The server MUST respond with a message containing an error
          (see <xref target="errors"/>), its own opening stream tag,
          or an XML text declaration followed by an opening stream
          tag.
        </t>
        <t>
          Except in the case of certain stream errors (see <xref
          target="errors"/>), the opening stream tag,
          &lt;stream:stream>, MUST appear in a message by itself.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Stream Errors" anchor="errors">
        <t>
          Stream level errors in XMPP are terminal. Should such an
          error occur, the server MUST send the stream error as a
          complete element in a message to the client.
        </t>
        <t>
          If the error occurs during the opening of a stream, the
          stream error message MUST start with an opening stream tag
          (see Section 4.7.1 of <xref target="RFC6120"/>) and end with
          a closing stream tag.
        </t>
        <t>
          After the stream error and closing stream tag have been
          sent, the server MUST close the connection as in <xref
          target="closing"/>.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Closing the Connection" anchor="closing">
        <t>
          Either the server or the client may close the connection at
          any time. Before closing the connection, the closing party
          MUST close the XMPP stream if it has been established.  To
          initiate the close, the closing party MUST send a normal
          WebSocket close message with an empty body. The connection
          is considered closed when a matching close message is
          received (see Section 1.4 of <xref
          target="RFC6455"/>).
        </t>
        <t>
          Except in the case of certain stream errors (see <xref
          target="errors"/>), the closing stream tag,
          &lt;/stream:stream>, MUST appear in a message by itself.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Stanzas">
        <t>
          Each XMPP stanza MUST be sent in its own message. A stanza
          MUST NOT be split over multiple messages. All first level
          children of the &lt;stream:stream> element MUST be treated
          the same as stanzas (e.g. &lt;stream:features> and
          &lt;stream:error>).
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Stream Restarts">
        <t>
          After successful SASL authentication, an XMPP stream needs
          to be restarted. In these cases, as soon as the message is
          sent (or received) containing the success indication, both
          the server and client streams are implicitly closed, and
          new streams needs to be opened. The client MUST open a new
          stream as in <xref target="setup"/> and MUST NOT send a
          closing stream tag.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Pings and Keepalives">
        <t>
          XMPP servers send whitespace pings as keepalives between
          stanzas, and XMPP clients can do the same thing. These extra
          whitespace characters are not significant in the protocol.
          Servers and clients SHOULD use WebSocket ping messages
          instead for this purpose.
        </t>
        <t>
          The XMPP Ping extension <xref target="XEP-0199"/> allows
          entities to send and respond to ping requests. A client
          sending a WebSocket ping is equivalent to pinging the
          WebSocket server, which may also be the XMPP server. When
          the XMPP server is not also the WebSocket server, a
          WebSocket ping may be useful to check the health of the
          intermediary server.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Use of TLS" anchor="tls">
        <t>
          TLS cannot be used at the XMPP sub-protocol layer because the
          sub-protocol does not allow for raw binary data to be sent.
          Instead, enabling TLS SHOULD be done at the WebSocket layer
          using secure WebSocket connections via the |wss| URI scheme.
          (See Section 10.6 of <xref target="RFC6455"/>).
        </t>
        <t>
          Because TLS is to be provided outside of the XMPP
          sub-protocol layer, a server MUST NOT advertise
          TLS as a stream feature (see Section 4.6 of 
          <xref target="RFC6120"/>), and a client MUST ignore any 
          advertised TLS stream feature, when using the XMPP 
          sub-protocol.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Stream Management">
        <t>
          Implications of, and recommendation to use, the XMPP Stream
          Management extension <xref target="XEP-0198"/> to be added.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Examples">
      <t>
        Examples will be added as soon as the WebSocket protocol
        specification is more stable.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>
        Since application level TLS cannot be used (see <xref
        target="tls"/>), applications which need to protect the privacy
        of the XMPP traffic need to do so at the WebSocket or other
        appropriate layer.
      </t>
      <t>
        The Security Considerations for both WebSocket (See Section 
        10 of <xref target="RFC6455"/> and XMPP (See Section 13 of 
        <xref target="RFC6120"/>) apply to the WebSocket XMPP 
        sub-protocol.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>
        This specification requests IANA to register the WebSocket XMPP
        sub-protocol under the "WebSocket Subprotocol Name" Registry
        with the following data:
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Subprotocol Identifier:">
            xmpp
          </t>
          <t hangText="Subprotocol Common Name:">
            WebSocket Transport for the Extensible Messaging and
            Presence Protocol (XMPP)
          </t>
          <t hangText="Subprotocol Definition:">
            RFC XXXX
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        [[NOTE TO RFC EDITOR: Please change XXXX to the number assigned
        to this document upon publication.]]
      </t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6120.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6121.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6202.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6455.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml4/reference.W3C.REC-xml-20081126.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xmpp.org/extensions/refs/reference.XSF.XEP-0124.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xmpp.org/extensions/refs/reference.XSF.XEP-0199.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xmpp.org/extensions/refs/reference.XSF.XEP-0206.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xmpp.org/extensions/refs/reference.XSF.XEP-0198.xml"?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
